i'm gonna surprise you with a little
shortfall you don't know when it's
coming okay so be ready
good
good anna
beautiful top spin on uh
get up pop up come on
back up
okay once you're there you gotta back up
good
good top spin
now back it up
okay
anna here's the problem when you are
playing back here and i surprise you
with a short ball you're reacting to it
too late by the time you realize the
ball is short then you start running now
you're going to have to hit the ball
literally on the run and you're going to
have a problem with your forehand
because of that okay so it's about ball
recognition it's easier said than done
you have to really track the ball and
try to read it study the ball
and then react to it accordingly but now
we're gonna practice short balls where
you know it's gonna be short okay so
stay there in the bass line i'm going to
drop you a short ball you know it's
going to be short and you just practice
hitting it from there
good job and a back pedal
and again
back pedal
pull it cross cord
come on
good work
and again back pedal
good work on it this is looking
fantastic
okay
the reason why i like you to backpedal
is because what happens to you not just
too many players is that when they get a
ball in this area right here behind the
service line and the middle between the
baseline and the service line they hit a
ball from here and they just wait here
they get stuck in what's called no man's
land
and you get stuck there a lot too so you
hit a forehand now you're just waiting
here
so what i recommend is that when you're
hitting balls from behind the surface
line you back pedal back to the baseline
immediately
can i ask you a question go ahead
so i'm always puzzled when do i go to
the net
good question so when the ball is inside
the service line that's when you can go
to the net
especially stay there right you can stay
there when the ball is like
well inside the service line you're
going to take that ball you're going to
follow it and the reason being
number one it's going to be too far to
go back it's too much of a distance and
also from here usually you're in a
pretty good position to put an easy
valley away because you're going to have
an easier forehand most likely if the
ball is sitting up a little higher so
it's okay to come in on those and try to
volley from here however it's going to
be more tricky to come to the net
there's a longer path
the forehand might not be as
aggressive potentially
and therefore it's a lot more simple for
you at this stage of your game to back
up to the baseline not get stuck here so
basically the simple answer is the
shorter the ball the more chances you
have to come to the net and play with a
volley here we go
and i'll back pedal that's a good
looking forehand there and again come
good work on a nice
and again come on
that's excellent good job another one
come on
you're hitting these balls so well
and again come on
excellent forehand now i'm going to go
on the other side
and i'm going to feed it to you so you
still know that it's coming to you so
you don't have to worry about ball
recognition
but the tricky part is the ball is going
to be coming through the court a little
bit
you need a break you're okay yeah i'm
fine you're fine all right so i'm going
to feed it to you you hit the same shot
back pedal back to the baseline and get
in there
okay so that ball i fed it a little bit
too short you could have come to the net
on that one right
good anna
okay get up to the ball a little more
get behind the baseline and again
good
up up up
excellent anna great job okay now
we're going to work on ball recognition
so i'm going to rally with you every now
and then i'll surprise you with a short
ball and let's see how you react to it
okay
here we go
good
good come on
much better on a great job nice
good backhand
that one you saw a little bit late you
noticed that yeah you hesitated just
that split second and you barely got to
it
good
again all right now look
anna
doing really good in the beginning
but now all of a sudden you're not
recognizing the ball as good as you were
in the very beginning so you have to
really focus on the ball continuously
every single time it's in play you
really have to concentrate on the ball
and try to read it as good as you can
otherwise you if you depend on the ball
to come to you it's not going to
sometimes deceiving when you play with a
coach or someone that's a really good
player
the ball comes really clean and then you
go out to the clinic and you see the
ball starts coming ugly all over the
place
so you have to really
not get comfortable back there when
you're playing with better players or
with a coach and really
treat every ball as it's the last one
the last one is it's very unpredictable
and then you're going to have to that
way you're going to learn ball
recognition you're going to start
reading the ball
otherwise if you kind of space out and
you kind of expect the ball to come to
you
you're not really observing the ball
well enough you know here we go
come come come
okay one more thing i have to
mention that's very very important is
that there's two types of balls there's
balls that you can set up on
and get in position there are balls that
are hit on the run i go feed it like up
high and make it land on the on the
service line go ahead
okay
perfect donna
okay so those are the two examples the
first one
i couldn't really position myself and
get planted and i literally hit it on
the run
so i was moving and hitting at the same
time
on the second one
i'd had to run up to the ball but there
was plenty of time to stop and position
my feet and get in place before i hit it
so those are the two differences there's
either balls that are hit on the run or
there are balls that are hit in a
stationary position so the key is that
you recognize when there is time to stop
and when there is not time to stop so
the last ball that i fed you was short
there was obviously no time to stop but
you still tried to stop you came in
there you tried to stop and hit that you
couldn't you had to run through that
ball
so it's another part of ball recognition
you have to recognize what type of ball
it is and then make a decision whether
you have to run through it or not i know
it's tricky it's not easy to do but you
got to really concentrate on the ball
and make a decision based on how the
ball is behaving that's coming over to
your side so being super alert super
high intensity being very concentrated
is going to help you okay
and attack it on it go
through run through and through good
work there now you still could have hit
a normal forehand though but that was on
the run yeah yeah but you could have
still gone like this and finish it a
little more good try though
good
much better on a much better go again
come on
more spin
good decision there very nice anna
you're doing much better on the short
boat but one more thing that we have to
talk about is the way you're approaching
a short ball and you're approaching it
very open so you always have the
tendency to run to the ball like this
and then once you get closer to it then
you do your turn and then you do all the
stuff that you're supposed to do on the
forehand
and we do it that way it turns into kind
of like a hectic forehand i'm sure it
feels rushed as you're hitting it so
remember what we learned very early on
maybe in our first lesson is the
forehand sequencing the first thing you
do when you see you're going to hit a
forehand when you observe the incoming
ball
is you're going to make a slight turn
towards the forehand side do the same
thing when you get a short ball instead
of running up like this you turn a
little bit now run with your racket to
the side
that's right shuffle like this no no
because that's gonna be too slow you do
wanna have the ability to run forward
but you already put your upper body in
more of a sideways position so that the
racket is more to the side
this is something that works really well
with my students i just tell them to
stick the strings out towards the side
as they run towards a short ball and
then once they get there they have one
step less to do and they feel like they
have so much more time
end up time the ball better they're much
more comfortable hitting it so basically
short ball you see a short you see your
forehead coming you recognize it short
you go like this and you run like this
rack it to the side okay let's try a few
um
from here i'm going to hand feed it and
then we'll try it out of a rally come
that was perfect actually do it again
a little bit late on that one
better you just think rack it to the
side do it again
ah there's the old one there's the old
one you're going like this
you're going here and then you're going
here
all right it doesn't look quite as
aesthetic
it looks a little bit awkward okay do it
again
better
there it is how's that feel better do
one more last one
better anna one more
last one anna come on
whoa
maybe maybe the best forehand you hit
all day
nice work anna
there you go i'm calling you anna now
yeah yeah
i'm switching it up no i'm just kidding
i don't know
you're anna yeah
that's a beautiful name by the way
we have we have anna and croatia too but
it's a one one n oh yeah yeah
now we do it
as a surprise so i'm not going to let
you know when the shortfall is coming
you have to
observe the ball you have to recognize
the ball super important that your high
intensity that you're observing and
concentrating on this little thing the
whole time
all right
then once you realize it's a short it's
a forehand anyway you're going to make
it turn towards the forehand side when
you realize it's short you're going to
run forward so this is the final test
let's see how you do on the short balls
we're going to rally i'm going to
surprise you
good
solid
go go go
another
dream well okay but still
i understand that it was very far from
you getting that ball but still make an
attempt yes
what i tell people is like you try to
get the ball off of three bounces and
then eventually if you keep trying you
get it for two bounces then one bounce
and if you never try you'll never have
the chance of getting that ball so
that's how you teach your
your body to be explosive and to react
to the ball quick enough by trying yeah
don't let balls go here we go come on
you know what that
you got it was a little further to your
side but i like the way you you attacked
that ball
okay i would put more distance between
you and the ball it seems like you're
too close here okay
good
come back to me right at me
go go go go go come on
good try i like the effort good try
not bad not bad at all
here we go anna come
pour in on a go
back in on a go
good attack head
not bad and back it up
come back to me
good
come on keep your feet moving longer
and again anna come
cut again anna come on
attack it go
not bad at all not bad at all i got four
more we're done four more and we're done
anna come on
come on
we're gonna this is the real deal
we're training hard
come on anna here we go
good
okay again when one thing is very
important when the ball is central when
it's in the middle of the court you have
to get out of the way this way you got
to go towards your backhand side
you can't just run straight at it it's
going to be too close
so let me give you one right here you
space out watch space out get out of the
way that was a bad feat do it again
middle of the court here right down the
center
better seriously
yeah you space out that way backhand
here it is
you know i like that one actually you
got a little bit bad luck because it hit
the top of the tape but it was a good
effort
four more
quirana
kurana
you stopped again you stopped i know you
had to keep going
exactly here we go
and here it is i don't come
not bad at all not bad at all
there it is anna yes that's the one anna
the short ball is tough
the short ball is a tricky ball
but he did a much better job
a lot of people find it very exhausting
when they have to move forward a lot i
noticed that i have to play in bikini i
understand but you know what
and then my sleeves
it's so hot it's super hot 12 o'clock
it's super hot today
but what i'm saying is this is more
exhausting than regular practice because
you're running up you're doing a lot
more running and a lot of recreational
players they again they get into a habit
when they're when they're playing back
here they get too relaxed and i'm saying
this happens to you a lot sometimes they
get too nonchalant too relaxed but here
they're not playing with high enough
intensity but here when you don't know
where the ball is going you see how much
effort you have to
generate how much intensity every ball
you got to give it a big effort because
you don't know what's going to happen
so this is one key that's called ball
recognition you did a lot better job
simply by being more aware of being more
concentrated having higher intensity you
did a better job and technically you did
a much better job
deciding when to stop when to run
through this will come up in a match
very frequently so it's a good thing
that we're practicing it because a lot
of players struggle with this ball so
good work nice
short balls today
you all right yeah come on 20 balls
i want you to hit everything cross-court
focus on
not missing come a little closer
here we go one
good anna here's two
come on
come closer to the ball three
come on anna
lower high four
here we go five
here we go six
come on seven
here we go eight
come on
nine here we go ten
come on anna eleven
here we go twelve
come on thirteen keep fighting
come on fourteen anna go
here's 15 on a go come on
now you're grinding hard 16.
come on
17 anna
here we go 18.
come on 19 and i go
match point
anna
you're working so hard today
this is amazing
bam
good work anna
wow
i think this is the tiredest i've ever
seen you hold on don't move don't move
don't move
you put sparkling water on your head
this is what i call the luxury life